Inventory of the Institute for Humane Studies Miscellaneous Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Institute for Humane Studies miscellaneous records
1955-1975
85023
Hoover Institution Archives
11 manuscript boxes (4.4 linear feet)
Institute for Humane Studies.
Access
Collection is open for research. Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The Institute for Human Studies was established in 1961 in Menlo Park, California by Dr. F.A. Harper. As a former economics professor at Cornell University, Dr. Harper made it his goal to establish an institute whose primary mission would focus on, “research and education in the conviction that greater understanding of human affairs and freedom would foster peace, prosperity, and social harmony.” Since its 1985 relocation to Fairfax, Virginia the institute has been associated with George Mason University where it continues today in the goals established by Dr. Harper.
Scope and Content of Collection
Collection comprised of sound recordings of lectures by various economists and other speakers delivered at the Institute for Humane Studies, relating to laissez-faire economic and political theory; correspondence, memoranda and financial records, relating to production of the festschrift Toward Liberty (1971) in honor of the Austrian-American economist Ludwig von Mises, and to a visit to the United States by the Austrian economist Friedrich A. von Hayek in 1975.
Hayek, Friedrich A. von (Friedrich August), 1899-1992.; Von Mises, Ludwig, 1881-1973.; Economics.; Laissez-faire.; Liberty.; Political science.
- Sound recordings of lectures, interviews, discussions, and meetings, 1955-1977; 141 sound tape reels (Box 1-10)
  - Armen Albert Alchian sound recordings, 1959 June
    - Economics as a Science of Choice, 1959 June 15 (Box 1)
      Availability
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008766
      Scope and Contents note
      Series: Microscopic View of Freedom (Individual)
      Alchian examines why people make the choices they do, illustrating his different points with a variety of scenarios.
    - Private Property, 1959 June 16 (Box 1)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008767
      Alchian argues that the individual is most free when it respects private property the most.
    - A group discussion with Armen Alchian, 1959 June 17 (Box 1)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008772
      Several men discuss the implications of Alchian's theories on property and liberty.
    - General Utility Approach to Case of Monopoly versus Competition, 1959 June 17 (Box 1)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008771
    - Legal and Economic Analysis of Monopoly and Competition, 1959 June 18 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008792
      Alchian examines monopoly and competition, especially as it applies to labor unions and particularly the Teamsters.
      The accessioned tape also includes a discussion with Morley of success of the federal government.
    - Problems of Monopoly: Discrimination and Restrictions on Entry, 1959 June 19 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008793
      Alchian examines the barriers of entry that a monopoly creates using examples such as bankers, used-car dealers, insurance agents, and university football programs.
    - Academic Tenure, 1959 June 22 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008797
      A talk on education, including school tuition, state support of education, and tenure.
    - Monopoly Theory and Inflation, 1959 June 23 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008800
    - Property Rights in Inflation, 1959 June 24 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008805
  - Herrell DeGraff sound recordings, 1957 June
    - Herrell DeGraff lecture, 1957 June 17 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008806
    - Herrell DeGraff lecture, 1957 June 19 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008809
    - Herrell DeGraff lecture, 1957 June 21 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008812
    - Herrell DeGraff lecture on technology in agriculture, 1957 June 24 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008813
    - Herrell DeGraff lecture on agriculture and the Commodity Credit Corporation, 1957 June 26 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008817
    - Herrell DeGraff lecture on agricultural economics, 1957 June 27 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008818
    - Herrell DeGraff lecture on agricultural economics, 1957 June 28 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008821
  - Aaron Director sound recordings, 1956 June
    - Aaron Director speech on monopoly as treated by the classical economists, 1956 June 02 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005821
    - Aaron Director speech on the classical liberal school, 1956 June 11 (Box 2)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005820
      Director examines the classical liberal school (particularly Smith, Mill, and Hume) and its relevance to the contemporary world. Topics include the division of labor, self-interest, decentralization of government, voluntary exchange, government intervention, civil liberty, and the relationship of political and economic freedoms.
    - Aaron Director speech on new conservatives, 1956 June 14 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005751
      Director speaks about the new conservatives. Critical of the group, he compares and contrasts them against the liberal school. He covers a variety of topics including, but by far not limited to: humanities and utilitarian education, materialism, agriculture and commerce, and their intellectual base of Marx.
    - Aaron Director speech on monopoly, 1956 June 15 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005753
    - Aaron Director speech on monopolies, 1956 June 16 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005814
      Director speaks about monopolies, not monopoly price theory.
    - Aaron Director speech on freedom of enterprise and monopoly, 1956 June 18 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005815
    - Aaron Director speech on full employment policy., 1956 June 20 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005816
      Director argues that the public policy of full employment is not a new concept; it is grounded in the idea of maximum output.
    - Aaron Director speech on housing prices, 1956 June 23 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0005752
      In this talk, Director discusses housing prices. He covers price controls, housing assistance, and zoning regulations.
  - Milton Friedman sound recordings
    - Milton Friedman seminar, 1955 June 17 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006849
      This recording sounds like a seminar Friedman had with a small audience, who regularly ask questions and for clarifications. The session has more of a feel of a workshop than a traditional lecture. The focus seems to be on wages and prices.
    - International Monetary Arrangements, 1955 June 20 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006850
      Friedman speaks about exchange rates in international trade. He is critical of fixed rates, instead advocating flexible rates.
    - Monopoly and the Role of the State, 1955 June 21 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006854
      Friedman discusses monopoly, antitrust, competition, and things that restrict competition such as patents, tariffs, and building codes.
    - A discussion with Milton Friedman, 1955 June 22 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006855
      Topics covered include: deposits, fractional reserve systems, the Federal Reserve, fixed exchange rates, gold, freedom of choice and monopoly. Throughout, Friedman and the others use a variety of goods to illustrate their point: bricks, Aspirin, paintings, hi-fi systems, etc.
    - Education and the State, 1955 June 23 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006858
      Friedman looks at the role of government in education. He believes that the state does have a concern in education, but he believes it should be left at funding of but not administration of education. Central to his analysis is the neighborhood-effect, in the process comparing education requirements to safety requirements in automobiles. He advocates a voucher system, though not by that name. He looks at the implications of his system on racial segregation.
    - Milton Friedman lecture on welfare considerations, 1955 June 24 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006859
      Friedman speaks about several issues all tied to welfare considerations. Topics include, but are not limited to: public housing, medical care--with particular emphasis on the British experience and the AMA's prohibition of foreign-trained doctors, and minimum wage laws.
    - Distribution of Income, 1955 June 25 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006862
    - Basic Principles of Liberalism, 1958 June 16 (Box 3)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006864
      Friedman analyzes the history of liberalism, from its roots in thinkers such as Adam Smith to his contemporary world where it is more commonly called libertarianism, a term Friedman dislikes due to its closeness to the word libertine.
    - Friedman-Kemp discussion, 1958 June 17 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006913
      A discussion on the role of government with an emphasis on a liberal society.
    - Role of Government in a Liberal Society, 1958 June 17 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006904
      Friedman looks at the role of government in a free society. Topics include: means and ends, unanimity without homogeneity, proportional representation, neighborhood effects and regulation, paternalism over the insane and children, occupational licensing, and parks.
      Among the audience is F.A. Hayek, who asks a question.
    - Problems of Maintaining Economic Stability, 1958 June 18 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006916
      In this speech, Friedman concentrates on the stability of money. In the process, he looks at backing a currency with commodities, counterfeiting, the dollar during the Civil War, the Federal Reserve System, a history of American monetary policy particularly during the Great Depression, and the role of government in monetary policy.
    - Discrimination in Employment and Education, 1958 June 19 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006919
      Dr. Friedman examines discrimination against ethnic and racial minorities. He believes a liberal, free-market system is the most beneficial system to these groups. He explains how the situations where discrimination is most prevalent is also where the situations are the most monopolistic. Other topics include, but are not limited to: taste vs. discrimination, free vs. fair speech, and right-to-work laws.
    - Distribution of Income and Welfare Actions of Government, 1958 June 24 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006920
    - Foreign Aid and Economic Development, 1958 June 25 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006947
      Friedman speaks about the intersection of foreign aid, tariffs, developed countries, and underdeveloped countries.
    - Is a Free Society Stable?, 1958 June 26 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006965
      With a "random comments" structure, Friedman ponders if a free country is stable on the long term. He analyzes this question noting that the history of the world has shown that despotism has been the natural state of man. He focuses his attention on the development and rejection of liberalism in the United Kingdom.
    - A group discussion with Milton Friedman, 1958 June 27 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0006979
    - Monopoly and the Social Responsiblity of Businessmen, 1968 June 27 (Box 4)
      Friedman speaks about monopolies, oligopoly, competition, labor unions, and cartels.
  - Friedrich A. von Hayek sound recordings
    - Coercion and the State, 1956 June 12 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0002673
      Part of the June 1956 series of lectures, The Creative Powers of the Free Civilization
      Hayek speaks about the use of coercion by the government and how this is different from coercion used by others. He argues that society institutes government to stop worse coercion by others. Saying coercion is not all the influence men can have on others, nor the state in which all choice is eliminated, he defines coercion as when a person makes it so that what he wants someone else to do is the least evil choice. Following, he spends much time explaining what is, what is not, and what leaves an opening for coercion. He believes law is a pre-condition of freedom. To him, coercion is objectionable because it is a form of destroying a mind; it does not allow a man to make proper choice. On how coercion by government differs from other coercions, he says the government usually acts with the threat of coercion, though he states taxation is a form of coercion. Hayek believes coercion is only justifiable to stop the harm of other persons than the coerced person; it cannot be used when the only people affected are the participants in an activity--Hayek uses the example of homosexuality. He finishes by mentioning John Stuart Mill.
      Topics discussed during the following question-and-answer session include, among others, conscription, taxation, Hayek versus Mill, Nazism/fascism, changing definitions of coercion, and monopoly and collusion versus coercion.
    - Law, Command, and Order, 1956 June 13 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008152
    - Man's Ignorance of Civilization, 1956 June 14 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008153
      Hayek speaks about how man's ignorance of various things prevents mankind from moving forward. Included, he looks at the individual and its relationship with civilization and culture.
    - Progress, 1956 June 15 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008154
      Hayek speaks about progress of society, what it is, what it means, whether it is inevitable, what causes it, and the importance of freedom in the equation.
    - Freedom, Reason, and Tradition, 1956 June 18 (Box 4)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008159
      Hayek looks at how various thinkers and noted people have approached freedom, liberalism, and reason through the years.
    - Equality, Value, and Merit, 1956 June 19 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008162
      Hayek speaks about compensation for work and its place in economic, political, and social systems.
    - Evolution and Significance of Rule of Law, 1956 June 21 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008163
      Hayek outlines the history of the rule of law from antiquity to the present.
    - Rule of Law (continued), 1956 June 23 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008164
      This talk is a continuation of his previous talk on the rule of law. This talk focuses more on what the rule of law is and its implications.
    - The Decemberline of Socialism and the Rise of the Welfare State, 1958 June 16 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008165
      Hayek delivers the first of a series of lectures on concrete dangers to a liberal society. He defines liberty as a state where state coercion is at a minimum. This lecture is an analysis of various experiments with socialism and the varying degrees of a welfare state throughout the West.
    - Social Security, 1958 June 18 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008170
      Hayek looks at the relationship of the individual and society when it comes to those than cannot provide for themselves. Included, he looks at the possibly of requiring people to purchase insurance to provide for them in times of need. While he looks at similar programs throughout the West, he concentrates on the United States' program. He feels it is a highest problem that the program is seen as an account someone pays into and not as a welfare program.
    - Taxation and Redistribution, 1958 June 20 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008171
      Hayek recalls the history of taxation and the aims of various taxes through history.
      The audio is of poor quality at the beginning.
      There is a second program on the original tape, as if someone (poorly) recorded over a group discussion with the talk by Hayek.
    - Housing and Town Planning, 1958 June 25 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008172
      Saying cities are what defines civilization from primitive cultures, Hayek looks at the role of government and society in defining city life. He argues that while private property rights are not the end-all decider of what one can do with land, the marketplace has been the most efficient allocator of resources--as opposed to central planning. He is harshly critical of rent control and housing cost ceilings. He also looks at government subsidized housing. He finished analyzing building regulations.
    - Meeting of the Institute for Humane Studies featuring F. A. Hayek, 1977 June 10 (Box 10)
      The first featured speaker is Lou Spadaro, the Institute's new president. His remarks are on "the why" of the Institute. He then introduces Professor Hayek.
      Hayek provides moral arguments for defeating socialism. He begins by saying the goals of the Institute are his, and that they both work to supply people with ideas for two reasons: helping business people defend their property and persuade politicians, and they provide intellectuals with the truth. Following, he lays the background for the talk by reflecting on the philosophical background of economists and how that affects their work. Getting to the thesis of his talk, he argues that one needs to make both the economic and moral arguments to defeat socialism, that one cannot do so with either by itself. Hayek then concentrates his time on the moral arguments. Touching on many facets, one such argument is calling the term "social justice" to be meaningless, arguing to demand the concept of social justice is to demand the destruction of western society. He ends by commenting on young people's relationship with classical liberalism. A short question-and-answer session follows the talk.
      Charles Koch functions as a master of ceremonies for the meeting and, with Ken Templeton, gives introductions.
      A recording of this meeting is also found in the Hayek papers, Object ID 86002.7.
  - Herber Heaton sound recordings, 1956 June
    - Medieval and Mercantilist Enterprise, 1956 June 13 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008179
      Heaton recalls the living conditions, both stereotypical and real, of Medieval civilizations in Europe. He uses this to compare and contrast it with contemporary conditions, values, and appraisals of Medieval times.
    - Period from 1450 to 1750, 1956 June 14 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008180
    - Industrial Revolution, 1956 June 16 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008183
      Heaton recalls the history of the Industrial Revolution.
    - The Widening Range of Competitive Enterprise in the 19th Century, 1956 June 18 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008184
      A talk on the industrial revolution.
    - Development of Entrepreneurship and Capital, 1956 June 20 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008185
      To Heaton, entrepreneurship encompasses
      1. One-man, family, or partnership
      2. Joint stock corporation
      3. Public Enterprise
      His discussion of capital focuses on its origin and accumulation.
    - Development of Entrepreneurship and Capital (continuation), 1956 June 21 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008190
    - Competitive Features of Modern Enterprise During Last 150 Years, 1956 June 22 (Box 5)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008191
      Heaton recalls the economic history of the West of the previous 150 years.
    - Balance Sheet: A Look at Freedom and Competitive Enterprise, 30's-50's, 1956 June 23 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008196
      Heaton speaks about the nationalization of industries in Great Britain and the United States in the first half of the 20th century.
  - John Jewkes sound recordings, 1959 June
    - Lecture on Great Britain as the highest profile welfare state, 1959 June 15 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008200
      A talk on Great Britain as the highest profile welfare state. He notes that the prime beneficiary of this system is the middle class, not the poor who the system was designed to benefit.
    - Lecture on location and productivity in manufacturing, 1959 June 16 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008201
      This talk is about the effect of location on manufacturers on productivity in Great Britain and what role the government should play in determining where businesses and factories are located.
    - Lecture on the National Health Service of Great Britain, 1959 June 17 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008202
      This talk is on the National Health Service of Great Britain and who should pay for medical care in an ideal system.
    - Lecture on health care in Great Britain, 1959 June 18 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008210
      Jewkes delivers a lecture continuing the previous lecture's focus on health care in Great Britain. He uses this examination to then look at the health care system of the United States.
    - Lecture on the nationalization of industries in Great Britain, 1959 June 19 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008212
      Jewkes look at nationalization of industries in Great Britain and how this relates to the welfare state.
    - First lecture on science and technology, 1959 June 23 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008213
    - Second lecture on science and technology, 1959 June 24 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008217
      Antagonistically, Jewkes delivers a second lecture on science and technology. He argues that education in science and technology is not more important than education in "the humane studies." He goes on to argue how knowledge in such studies is more important than faster advancement through technology or science. He believes there is a danger in oversupply of scientists.
    - Lecture on John Kenneth Galbraith and the book The Affluent Society, 1959 June 25 (Box 6)
      Use copy available. Hoover Identifier 85023_a_0008218